So what do you mean when you talk about
psychization? [snorts] How do you recognize yourself
[snorts] How do you recognize yourself
doing it and why is it a problem?
>> So psychologization
psychologization
the uh the term I came up with is
basically it means like when you're
doing u like uh self-explaining to
yourself or explaining
uh as to why and how things happen to
yourself to help you cope.
um you can't help doing it in the
beginning. Obviously, the the more
successful your practice is, the less
and less you'll be doing it and
eventually you wouldn't be doing any
psychization because you're free from
suffering. So, it's like the the
internal mental response to being
affected by dooka, you know, like a
really unrestrained person will just act
with a body and punch or steal or do
stuff to get what they want so that they
don't suffer. Somebody who doesn't do
that but then still affected by the
world internally, they will have to find
ways of coping. So then it's like
rationalizations, justifications, explanations. Sometimes
justifications, explanations. Sometimes
it's not even like necessarily that kind
of coarse form of avoiding
responsibility mentally. Well, I did it
because of this. I know I couldn't have,
but but I did it because this is what
happened and they said this and this and
therefore it was deserved. That's
already like it's a cover up. Even if it
was the most deserved action that you
did, if you're having to explain it to
yourself, it's a cover up. Means you're
covering up the discomfort of it, the
discomfort of responsibility of it. So
that's why it's a problem. That's why
it's unh wholesome because it always
partakes in some degree of ignorance of
a vija of a cover up.
So it could even be a subtler form as
well, which would be like uh you know
like the whole practice is about
understanding. But then obviously in order to
But then obviously in order to
understand the mind you need to start to
see the mind in order to see the mind
well like you need to have been
practicing the the restraint and
withdrawal from all the things and
actions that you make that obscure the
mind. Uh and that takes time to develop
that it takes takes faith to stick to as
well to keep doing it. So then what
people would often kind of become
trapped by is that
the need to understand things gets
conflated with uh figuring things out.
So collecting the bits of information
making sense out of it in my mind equals
understanding and that's another
psychization that's another cover up of sorts. So now
that's another cover up of sorts. So now
when dooka happens well that's just the
pasa that's affected by the you know
sense sense object's eye this comes
together then this happens that this is
the response then that's the response
okay I'm cleared
but again you can't as I said you can't
just magically stop doing that there's
going to be some tendency to explain
it's not going to be perfect but if you
keep looking beyond it as in like okay I
am still putting pieces together and
trying this and trying that but overall
when I'm touched by suffering do I need
to do anything
is [snorts] there an impulse
a compulsion
to explain it to myself
what happened here why
why do I have to do that
why can't I just understand things as
they are
without needing to go through the
self-explanatory loops
loops
Why can't in the scene just be the
scene? What I've seen is just to the
extent that it's seen. I don't need to
be saying what happened behind the
scenes to feel comfortable with this
to feel comfortable with this
in perceived there's just perceived in
the felt there will be just the felt.
Why can't I stay with that the most the
broadest of the most ambiguous yet as I said real
of the most ambiguous yet as I said real
estate
stopping short real as such or is the
impulse to complete the sentence
internally of what has just occurred
taken for granted and I always just act
out of it.
So it's like a deeply rooted
psychological mental habit need that
comes from that need to just deal with
suffering and that's why it's
fundamentally just inseparable from
Avijia.
So where would you then um
start to try to identify um because I
think for anybody who's taking on the
precepts trying to develop restraint and
um [snorts] sila to a certain extent
>> there is the very easy tendency of
whenever you start to suffer to say oh
well it must be because of failure in
morality and this or that.
It doesn't seem to me like that's always
100% wrong. Like it can be accurate, but
when when does that basically how do you
make sure that you're doing that?
>> Well, I think that's that's what I mean
like stopping the mids sentence. The
first half of the sentence would be just
the thoughts that the mind came up with
which often might be effectual. That's
why I said like in the previous
conversations like oh I did that because
he said this and he was deserving it and
he was really unpleasant and I needed to
put him in his place. And that might be
100% true
those facts but the fact is if you acted
out of ill will that's always on you
that part. So this is the same like uh
you start keeping the precepts start
trying to figure things out but
as things arise as challenges present
themselves you kind of say recognize to some extent
you kind of say recognize to some extent
like okay well the problem here is maybe
you know I slipped in the precepts I
acted out so that's why this and it's
like you will you will feel the line so
to speak you will see where where that
recognition and that say like thought
process comes up to a certain extent and
when it becomes emotionally charged
that's the difference here. So it's like
oh it's because but now there is this
kind of vacuum left of unfulfilled
pressure. Well let me repeat this again
this same information
to feed this pretty much this this this
this pressure is there and that's now
passing the mids sentence. Now you're
adding out. So it feels again I say
mid-sentence because you start from the
position of overdoing making those
mistakes doing psychologizations. But in
reality the extent that it has arisen
it's a it's sufficient enough. It's
already a finished sentence. The fact
that you feel ambiguous about it does
not make the mental sentence unfinished.
That's your own view that paints it that
way and then you keep adding more. But
again the framework will never be
satisfied. So they're never going to end the the
So they're never going to end the the
proliferation of adding more and needing
more information. See, if you never see
the problem of that mental habit of
psychologizing, [snorts]
it's infinitely hungry.
Like there is no end to then you needing
new things, new angles, new
interpretations, new explanations, new
techniques, new practices to keep
feeding that furnace basically because
the things become stale if you just
repeat the same psychological pity. They
don't offer the relief anymore. So you
need to embellish, you need to change,
you need to find a different
um a different take on those things. And
it's never ending because again that's
not where the root of the problem was.
>> And so in terms of there's one sutra
that says one cannot come to the end of
duka without understanding the four
noble truths. Such a thing is not
possible. >> You have to understand the four noble
>> You have to understand the four noble
truths
>> to bring an end to to suffering.
>> So
so one can read that and say well I have
to now understand.
>> Yeah. So what is suffering? What is what
is the cause of suffering? Okay. Well,
the Buddha says this in this suta and
that d.
>> Yeah. That's why again learning is
indispensable. You need to have the right information,
You need to have the right information,
right instructions. We spoke about it so
many times. At the same time like if you
are not transparent enough as I said you
will often confuse the learning for making
often confuse the learning for making
connections between mental information
as in sorry you will confuse
understanding for mere learning so I
know the sutras I know the pi I know all
the terms how they connect I can explain
them it's like yeah that's the
informationational level that is
necessary but does that
informationational level or have Have
you also learned about through
information the necessity of
self-transparency and precepts
that can then elevate your
merelyformational level to the actual
practice. Why? Well, because if you're
truly understanding those terms, you
would not be affected by duka
emotionally. You wouldn't need to do anything on
You wouldn't need to do anything on
account of the aris duka because you are
not affected by it to begin with. So if
that criteria, if that reference point,
that understanding leads to freedom from
suffering here and now at the most
deepest existential level, you you are
free. If that criteria is not known, learned,
If that criteria is not known, learned,
maintained, discerned,
you're not understanding anything. Your
understanding is just understanding
relative to information that you have.
And often again as I said even in in my
own practice in my process of like
learning and collecting I remember like
you know reading this book or that book
and the suda translations and stuff and
and often it was just like a like almost
like a comparative study
and I didn't understand why it was wrong
back then to what extent it was wrong
but I remember I couldn't quite make
sense how would this free the liability
to suffer here on the as I said the most
personal level there was just nothing
there. It was just oh you just do this.
So it kind of almost became again like
another as I said mechanical method of
just just just just fitting the puzzles
of the information of the pieces of
connecting finding angle writing about
it kind of fleshing it out and so on.
It's like but here and now what is your
motivation to do that? Have you included
that in yourformational
um Jenga puzzle?
[crying] And it's like no that's like
that's kind of like assumed that those
things will just happen by themselves
that you know purification of your own
relationship with your own mind and your
feelings and acting out body speech and
mind it's like oh so then all the
information in the world will not free
you from suffering
like you can you can read and par study
sutas all you want it will take you in
the direction of as I said um
uhformational knowledge that's now
filled the place for understanding for
you. Again, somebody's going to think,
"Ah, so I must stop reading." No, you
should by all means keep reading, study
sutas, understand the terms, get to the
bottom of like the key poly terms so
that you have your own clear view as to
what that means and you can explain to
somebody else. But at the same time
maintain the reference point as to okay
I'm doing this and keeping an eye onto
my overall liability to suffer and act
out of lust act out of aversion because
if these things are understood this
should be diminishing if I'm truly
thinking along the lines of the correct
dharma after I finish the thinking the
desire will be far away
the the possibility of ill will be far
away not that I be immediately it can
come back if I become careless but it
will be far away it won't be like 5
minutes later craving is there sensual
thoughts are there I was irritated by
this no there would be the actual samadi
as the result of right thinking along
the the lines of the right dharma
>> you say it's because you're actually
living that uh what you what you're
reading you know you're actually seeing
what you're reading
>> well yeah that's the point like you're
reading it you need to transcend the
level of like I'm reading it for
theformational purposes I'm reading I
think it's so to see those things here
and now on the level of my own mind on
the level of my own experience and I
said that in old talks like I remember
that you know I would be walking back
and forth and like you know
contemplating and so on and then
occurred to me I was like okay viana
like it's consciousness we translated
consciousness and in this language it's
translated like that in that language
like but what what is it like I know
it's consciousness it's like okay but
what is consciousness
[snorts] it's like but instead of Oh, let me find
it's like but instead of Oh, let me find
another definition now that I can say
that's what consciousness is and like
shift from one information. Oh, vana.
Oh, yeah. Well, via is consciousness.
Oh, but what's conscious? Well,
consciousness is actually and then
whatever adopt some other view like
well, but that's still not like telling
me what consciousness is here and now.
Those are just like passing information
from one to the other to the other onto
the next information. Like, so what is
consciousness? When I say consciousness,
consciousness, what am I referring? Like
when I say left arm, I know I'm
referring to this thing.
But when I say consciousness, what am I
referring in my in this space and time
of my experience as a whole? What am I
referring to when I say consciousness?
And I thought, oh well, that's a good
question. It's like hold on, let's take
something simpler. When I say rupa, what
am I referring to? When I say va, what
am I referring to? Oh, it's feeling.
What am I referring? Where is that
thing? Can I describe it in any other
terms? >> And that's how you understand it.
>> And that's how you understand it.
>> Well, exactly. That's how you get to see
the actual phenomena that you are
referring to
>> without having
>> without having to adopt another external
standpoint. >> Explanation
>> Explanation
>> explanation for as long as you're not
seeing those phenomena as
livingly designated here and now so to
speak. They are at the arms length. They
are from the external standpoint
uh uh they are theoretical. They are
abstract. Even if you know in and out
the ethmology, the root, the language,
what it refers to, you can compare it to
six different takes on it for you. It's
still not pertaining to the right level
and it's still not freeing you from
suffering. And it never will because no
amount of information can bridge that
gap. So
So
learning is necessary but learning will
be a lot more efficient, a lot less
likely to become uh proliferated in
these abstractly theoretical ways that
are confused for the or this is the
truth that I know now although I'm not
free from suffering if it's paired with
the actual mental training withdrawal
from the unh wholesome actions taming of
the mind then
you wouldn't need even half of the
information to See the things that those
very sutas talk about
vana do you see vana [snorts]
do you see the aggregate of vana like
for yourself not do you see another take
someone else's writing of what vyana is
when I see vyana I think about someone
else's words
like no do I see that phenomenon
without using any words do I just in the
same sense like I say my left arm I
don't need to keep saying to myself what
my left arm is. I see it
>> mentally.
>> I recognize it what it is.
>> Evening duka suffering
>> anything. Do you see?
>> Well, that's the whole point.
>> Suffering
>> you I it occurred to me in regard to vi
I remember. But then exactly. So what is
duka then? What is tantaha then
being free from suffering? Well what is
that? What do I mean by that? Like I
have a vague notion of freedom but what
does that actually entail for me? What
do I think it is? Am I clear on that or
I'm just like just going along with this
like halfbaked
uncclarified mostly obscured
ideas that came on account of even the
right information but then never like
pushed further internally. It's not can
I it's not just about can I explain
tanha duke or consciousness
in some words.
>> Can I see it for myself without even
explaining it?
>> Yeah.
>> When I say tanha can I immediately see
what that refers to?
He says, "Chittita, can I see what that
refers to?" So the sutas become a very
different ball game. Then if that
becomes your standard of understanding
everything that you've been taking for
granted in reading because it makes
sense. It's written and there is a
context you follow. You understand it on
some level.
>> It's easy.
>> But it's like oh but now
obviously this addresses like you know
the the the training in higher mind you
know the five types of thought that
everybody think they can do it. just
think the opposite and do this. But the
whole thing remember that applies to
like the higher mind training. It's like
okay so the higher chitta so am I even
seeing the lower chitta like when it
says chitta do I see that phenomenon of
chitta here and now or do I just have a
vague idea about it that pleases me and
makes sense and then I build on top on
top of that
>> it's like oh so then I got to see the
mind and then this whole
everything else that follows in the suta
will probably read very differently then
if I see the chitta it will probably a
lot more acute direct efficient
instruction ction than just oh think the
opposite and hope for the best type of
thing. Wish love to everybody and so on.
It's like no it's like directly seeing
the chitta and then when he has these
thoughts you also provide this context.
When he has those thoughts well you
provide this context
on that level. It's like oh it's getting
too tight I'm loosening it's getting too
loose I'm tightening it. Tune is
becoming perfect.
>> Well you're understanding the mind
>> of course and the mind is calming down
as a result of it. And as he says you
know the calm mind the joy arises the
joy the clear seeing the clear seeing
the understanding the liberation.
>> The problem is obviously the
informationational knowledge can be very
convincing. >> Yeah. And and
>> Yeah. And and
>> so then you you end up of course. Yeah.
So you end up very convinced and safe in
your explanatory system
>> of ideas of satisfying ideas that
provide safety. Uh and you know answer
to everything because you read all the
sutas. Well, that's this and this and
this this this. So, this internal level
of your intention in regard to that and
everything else we talk about will also
become part of something that you psy
through psychologization explain back
and have answer for. It's like so why
would I why would I need to but I
already understood it. I have an answer
for it. So you need to that person any
person needs to be transparent enough to
recognize yeah but and ask themselves
but am I free from suffering without
having to explain anything without
having to do anything is the suffering
still touching me or not because if
that's absent no amount of information
can make you open your eyes it will just
distract you further so to speak
>> and that's what
>> that's what I think said in one of the
letters when apparently some logician
was given sutas to read and he said well
this weird like this is all just mere
tology cuz he could not conceive that
this is to be done. He was approaching
everything through uh information of
ABC. So if it's this then it's this then it's
So if it's this then it's this then it's
that. I read it sutas finished.
So he thought sutas are just
self-explanatory statements
which if you don't have the idea of
training they are.
Oh you'll be free from ignorance. You'll
be free from Avija when you make the
effort and free yourself from Avija.
Uhhuh. Okay. Well, thank you. I know
that now. Therefore, my work is
complete. It's like, no. Have you
trained? Have you done the things in
between that the so to say? But if even
the things in between the training is
taken as self-explanatory statements,
then you're never going to take on
anything. And then even if you take on
the practices of keeping the precepts
and training and stuff but still not
using that internal living criteria of
can I be touched by suffering you know
whether I have a perfect explanation and
technique to manage it or not uh you
will fall again into one view or the
other that would be semi-abstract
semi-csychology kind of psychologizing
uh these these layers of of avoiding
responsibility covering it up building
up a system that pro provides safety
through explanation.
Because familiarity of explanation that
gets confused for understanding.
Oh, it makes sense. I pleases me. Yeah.
Not like makes sense. I can't be touched
by suffering. Makes sense equals pleases
me. Therefore, or what pleases me equals
makes sense.
So, it's fine to like, as I say, you
can't just switch it off. The the the
tendency of thinking like that.
But you certainly can make the effort
and not lose the the sight of the bigger
picture, which is sure I'm
contemplating. I'm collecting
information. I'm connecting dots in
space and time of how things work. But
also to bring it back home on the level
of in the scene, the scene is seen.
That's it. There is no other loops of
having to add extra tidbits of knowledge
to make sense because it's already
understood on the level it has arisen
>> and that can only be done if that
criteria and the widest reference point
is understanding leads to freedom from
suffering. freedom from a liability to
suffer. Understanding anything,
understanding rupa, understanding the
term vinana, understanding the term
duka, understanding term va. Pick a
term, any aggregate, noble truth,
whatever. Understand it. That means you are unable
Understand it. That means you are unable
to suffer even if you want to. So that
that criteria must remain like like like
clarified and and and and acknowledged
throughout because that's what will keep
you in check when you go through your
ramblings and roamings mentally and you
know habits. This will still keep you
relatively aligned.
But if you dismiss that then well good
luck.